Jack: So, what are the roles in
coding teams and software development
Leah: Project Managers are
responsible for budgets, risk,
scheduling and contract management.
They might not know the product
that they are creating that well,
but they are in control overall.
Jack: Product Owners are more
or less analysts and concentrate
on a product and its features.
Leah: Team Lead is the role given to a
developer with leadership qualities and
who can maintain communication between
remote development teams and clients.
Jack: Tech Lead has the greatest
knowledge and can solve problems not
linked with the development, they
are also known as the 'architect'.
Leah: Full Stack Developer is a programmer
not specialised in one area but has a
broad range of skills and can implement
a solution on every architectural layer.
Jack: Front End developers are the point
of contact between the end client or
user and the system being developed.
Leah: Back End Developer is the
programmer focused mainly on
developing logic and data layers.
Jack: QA Lead is responsible for
building the quality assurance team
and its management and is accountable
for relations between QA team members.
Leah: QA engineer is responsible for
preparing tools that allow for automating
processes to verify software quality.
Jack: Testers are responsible
for conducting manual tests
doing system verification.
They will try alternate paths
to help eliminate any errors.
Leah: UI Designers are responsible
for preparing, designing the
user interface and transferring
content, style, and graphics.
Jack: UX Designers are responsible
for the users experience analysing
user behaviour and changing human
computer interaction methods.
Leah: There are two different
approaches to coding teams and
methods for conducting projects.
One is a 'traditional' development
team and the other is a 'scrum' team.
A traditional development teams is
based on a hierarchy between team roles,
so there are leaders and managers.
This allows the project manager
control and it's always clear who
is responsible for making decisions.
Jack: In a 'scrum' development
team there isn't an organisational
leader, it is self-managed.
Team roles don't overlap, and team members
decide work principles on their own,
giving a degree of autonomy, which can
help make the experience more enjoyable.
However, even though a scrum team
is self-managing, the structure in
place, ensures, that there is a person
responsible, the 'scrum master' for
the right flow of the project and
that everyone in the team is on track.
Leah: So why is teamwork
important in coding?
When team members work together
effectively towards a common goal like
developing a product, this will provide
the best experience for end users.
Developers, quality assurance personnel
and software testers should all
work closely together as this can
help to increase efficiency, enhance
creativity as well as drive innovation.
It can also help to get a product
to market faster and prevent coding
and other development mistakes.
Jack: When team members feel comfortable
expressing themselves, they can gain more
confidence in expressing and introducing
new ideas, concepts and approaches.
This can encourage creativity which may
result in innovations that may not have
been thought of in the planning stage.
Leah: When teams don't work well
together, team members will be more
inclined to follow their own goals or
show a lack of commitment to a project.
The fear of conflict or avoidance
of accountability may lead to
trust issues and prevent team
members from sharing ideas.
So, it's important for teams to work
on their skills of communication and
collaboration to support efficiency,
creativity, and innovation.